Alamance County CR.001
State Archives of North Carolina
- Land and Property Records, CR.001.4; Alamance County (N.C.); Clerk of Superior Court; Clerk of Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions; Register of Deeds
  - Resale of Land and Foreclosures, 1921-1968; CR.001.409; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.
    - Record of Resale of Land by Trustees and Mortgages, 1921-1968; CR.001.409; 201.112.1; 2014.4.59; 2018.7.91; CR.001.409.1 - CR.001.409.7; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court (Item Record of Resale of Land by Trustees and Mortgages, Box Unprocessed Record of
      Twentieth-century record of land sold under foreclosure by trustees and mortgagees. Case papers from foreclosure actions may be filed in some counties as civil actions concerning land (325) or as miscellaneous land records (408).
      Processed: 1921-1961
      v1 1921-1926; v2 1926-1929; v3 1929-1930; v4 1930-1933; v5 1933-1937; v6 1937-1952; v7 1951-1961
      Unprocessed: 1930-1968
    - Record of Foreclosures, 1961-1968; CR.001.409; 201.114.1; 2016.5.28; CR.001.409.8 - CR.001.409.9; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court (Item Record of Foreclosures)
      CR.001.409.8 (1961-1965); CR.001.409.9 (1965-1968)
- Estates Records, CR.001.5; Alamance County (N.C.); Clerk of Superior Court; Clerk of Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions; Register of Deeds
  This series contains records related to the administration of deceased persons' property. [See also series 3, Court Records, subseries 922, Orders and Decrees and Special Proceedings, and series 4, Land and Property Records, for other records related to estates.]
  - Estates/Accounts, Dockets, 1849-1969; CR.001.EA; 201.45; Accounts; Alamance County (N.C.); Clerk of Superior Court; Clerk of Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions; Register of Deeds
    Contains bound volumes of account, inventory, and/or settlement records related to the administration and settling of deceased persons' property. These include Record of Estates (pre-1868), Record of Accounts (post-1868), Accounts of Sales and Resales of Estates, Record of Inheritance Tax, Inventories of Estates, Amounts Paid Indigent Children, and Record of Settlements. Prior to 1868, volumes entitled record of estates may include inventories, accounts and final settlements of estates, and guardians' accounts. After 1868, these volumes in most counties contain only inventories, accounts of sales and annual accounts of administrators and executors.
    - Record of Accounts, 1869-1951; CR.001.501; 1989.5.24; 201.45.1; 2012.5.198; CR.001.501.1 - CR.001.501.7; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court (Item Record of Accounts)
    - Estates not Exceeding $300.00 [CSC 1], 1957-1963; CR.001.501; 201.45.2; 2014.4.62; CR.001.501.8; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court (Item Estates not Exceeding $300.00)
      Estates not Exceeding $300.00, known in the county and indexes as "Volume CSC 1."
    - Inheritance Tax Record, 1924-1969; CR.001.513; 201.57.1; 2012.7.134; CR.001.513.1; CR.001.513.2 - CR.001.513.4; Alamance County (N.C.) (Volume Inheritance Tax Record, Item Inheritance Tax Record)
      Twentieth-century record of settlement of tax assessed on estates worth more than $2000 provided to the clerk of superior court by the State Commissioner of Revenue. Statements include names of deceased and administrator or executor, approximate valuation of estate, and heirs or devisees. Loose papers concerning inheritance tax are filed in the series of estates records.
    - Inventories and Accounts of Sales, 1849-1932, 1943-1951; CR.001.514; 1974.11.04; 201.58.1; 2014.4.63; CR.001.514.1 - CR.001.514.7; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court (Item Inventories and Accounts of Sales)
      Record of initial inventories of estates filed by administrators and executors; before 1868, may also include accounts of sale. May be recorded in series of record of estates/accounts (501), which see.
      Inventories and Accounts of Sales: v. 1 1849-1854; v. 2, p. 1-236 1854-1858; v. 2, p. 237-456 1854-1858; v.3 1859-1863; v. 4 1884-1897; v. 5 1897-1916; v. 6 1916-1932; v. 7 1943-1951
    - Record of Amount Paid to Indigent Children, 1919-1954; CR.001.515; 201.115.1; 2014.4.69; CR.001.515.1; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court (Item Record of Amount Paid to Indigent Children)
    - Record of Settlements, 1870-1951; CR.001.518; 1974.11.4; 201.61.1; 2012.5.171; CR.001.518.1 - CR.001.518.10; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court (Item Record of Settlements)
      Volumes of settlements or final accounts submitted by administrators and executors after the complete distribution of the assets of an estate.
      1870 - 1891; 1891 - 1908; 1908 - 1918; 1919-1925; 1925-1932; 1929-1943; 1939-1943; 1943-1947; 1947-1951; 1951
  - Estates/Accounts, Papers, 1856-1979; CR.001.508; 1977.8.8; 201.52.1; 2017.3.5; 2018.7.93; CR.001.508.1 - CR.001.508.21; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Administrative Office of the Courts; Clerk of Superior Court (Box Estates Records, Box Unprocessed Estates Records)
    Alphabetical (processed); file number (unprocessed)
    Contains loose estate papers, which may include appointments and renunciations of executors and administrators; administrators' and guardians' bonds; inventories; accounts of sale; annual accounts; final settlements; civil actions and executions involving administrators, executors, and guardians; and actions in equity or special proceedings involving property of an estate.
    Processed estates records (1856-1949) are arranged in alphabetical order and housed in 21 archival document boxes numbered CR.001.508.1-21 (Adams-Zachery).
    Unprocessed estates records (1946-1972) located in 3.29.A.67-113 are in file number order (#1-4462 and X838-1000) and housed in 47 record center boxes.
    Unprocessed estates records (1968-1979) located in 3A.6.B.11-26 are in file number order (68E1 thru 79E642) and housed in 19 record center boxes.
  - Administrators, Executors, and Guardians, 1849-1968; CR.001.AG; Alamance County (N.C.); Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.
    Contains bound volumes and/or loose papers of bonds, appointments, and accounts of administrators, executors, and guardians. The loose papers consist primarily of guardians' records; loose administrators' bonds are generally filed in subseries 508, Estate/Accounts, Paper.
    For some counties, see also Record of Probate (Estates) or Minutes, Probate Court in Estates Records subseries 519, Miscellaneous Estates Records.
    - Administrators' Bonds, 1882-1902; CR.001.503; 201.47.1; CR.001.503.1 - CR.001.503.3; Alamance County (N.C.) (Item Administrators' Bonds)
      Volumes arranged chronologically. Loose bonds are filed in the series of Estates Records (508). After 1919, see Appointment and Record of Administrators (504).
    - Appointment of Administrators, Executors and Guardians, 1869-1902; CR.001.504; 1996.5.10; 201.48.1; CR.001.504.1; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court (Item Appointment of Administrators, Executors and Guardians)
    - Record of Administrators, 1902-1968; CR.001.504; 201.48.2; 2012.5.170; CR.001.504.2 - CR.001.504.16; Alamance County (N.C.) (Item Record of Administrators)
    - Guardian Returns, 1849-1868; 1879-1951; CR.001.509; 201.53.1; 2012.5.216; CR.001.509.1 - CR.001.509.6; Alamance County (N.C.) (Item Guardian Returns)
      1849-1868; 1879-1927; 1927-1940; 1940-1945; 1945-1950; 1950-1951
    - Guardian Record, 1954-1963; CR.001.509; 201.53.2; 2012.5.196; CR.001.509.7; Alamance County (N.C.) (Item Guardian Record)
    - Record of Guardians and Trustees, 1963-1968; CR.001.509; 201.53.3; 2012.5.197; CR.001.509.8; Alamance County (N.C.) (Item Record of Guardians and Trustees)
    - Guardians' Records, 1878-1949; CR.001.510; 1977.08.08; 201.54.1; CR.001.510.1 - CR.001.510.6; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court (Box Guardians' Records)
      Loose guardians' papers arranged alphabetically by surname of wards, and volumes of guardians' accounts (but see 509). Papers may include appointments, oaths and bonds of guardians; annual accounts; final settlements; civil actions and executions involving guardians; and actions in equity or special proceedings involving the property of a ward's estate. These records also include indigent wards for whom the clerk of superior court served as receiver. If the father of the wards can be determined from the papers, they are filed with the estate of the deceased rather than with the guardians' records.
      Albright - Wyrick
    - Guardians' Bonds, 1882-1953; CR.001.511; 201.55.1; 2012.7.126; CR.001.511.1 - CR.001.511.5; Alamance County (N.C.) (Item Guardians' Bonds)
      Volumes arranged chronologically. Loose bonds are filed in either the estates records (by decedent) or the guardians' records (by ward). After 1919, see Appointment and Record of Guardians (506).
      1882-1894; 1889-1909; 1910-1931; 1930-1943; 1943-1953
  - Dower and Widows' Year, 1878-1968; CR.001.507; 201.51; Alamance County (N.C.)
    Contains volumes relating to the apportionment of widows' dower rights in the real property of her deceased husband, and the allocation of a sufficiency of provisions to enable her to support herself and family during the first year after his death while the estate was being settled.
    Some papers concerning dower and widows' year's support are also filed in Estate Records subseries 508, Estate/Accounts, Papers, under the name of the deceased husband.
    - Record of Dowers, 1878-1951; CR.001.507; 1989.05.24; 201.51.1; 2012.7.168; CR.001.507.1 - CR.001.507.2; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court (Item Record of Dowers)
      1878 - 1933
      Volume 2, 1937-1951
    - Widows' Year Support, 1928-1968; CR.001.507; 1989.05.24; 201.51.2; CR.001.507.3 - CR.001.507.4; Alamance County (N.C.) (Item Widows' Year Support)
  - Records of Receivers and Trustees, 1884-1968; CR.001.517; 201.111; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Alamance County (N.C.); Clerk of Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions; Clerk of Superior Court; Register of Deeds
    Contains records pertaining to receivers and trustees of estates. May include volumes of Record of Receivers of Estates and Record of Inventories and Accounts of Assignees.
    - Record of Receivership, 1925-1955; CR.001.517; 201.111.1; 2014.4.56; CR.001.517.1; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court (Item Record of Receivership)
    - Record of Trustees, 1941-1962; CR.001.517; 201.111.2; 2014.4.60; CR.001.517.2; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court (Item Record of Trustees)
    - Trust Under Wills, 1961-1968; CR.001.517; 201.111.3; 2014.4.65; CR.001.517.3; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court (Item Trust Under Wills)
- Marriage, Divorce, and Vital Statistics, CR.001.6; Alamance County (N.C.); Clerk of Superior Court; Clerk of Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions; Register of Deeds
  This series contains vital records pertaining to major life events such as marriage, divorce, adoption (restricted by statute), immigration and naturalization, death, and disinterment/reinterment.
  - Marriage Records, 1854-1868; CR.001.MA; Alamance County (N.C.); Clerk of Superior Court
    Marriage bonds are statements of intent to marry that were attested by the prospective groom before the clerk of court in the bride's county of residence. Typically, one or more bondsmen signed as security for the forfeiture of the penal sum (originally 50 pounds, increased to 500 pounds in 1778, and to $1,000 in the nineteenth century) should the marriage not occur or prove to be illegal.
    Contains records pertaining to marriage in the form of bonds, licenses, registers, and/or certificates. Abstracts exist for the Marriage Bonds. Marriage Licenses prior to 1868 are filed with the marriage bonds. Most Marriage Bonds give the names of the groom, bride, bondsmen, and witnesses, the name of the person performing the rites, and, toward the end of the period, the names of parents.
    - Marriage Bonds, CR.001.601; 1991.5.40; 201.63.1; Alamance County (N.C.)
      Includes boxes of marriage bonds and certificates (1741-1868), arranged alphabetically by groom. Marriage bonds are statements of intent to marry that were attested by the prospective groom before the clerk of court in the bride's county of residence. Typically, one or more bondsmen signed as security for the forfeiture of the penal sum (originally 50 pounds, increased to 500 pounds in 1778, and to one thousand dollars in the nineteenth century) should the marriage not occur or prove to be illegal. Most marriage bonds give the names of the groom, bride, bondsmen and witnesses, the county in which filed and the date. If accompanied by a certificate of marriage, the information may also include the date of marriage, the name of the person performing the rites, and, towards the end of the period, the names of parents. The more than 170,000 marriage bonds in the Archives have been abstracted. Volumes of abstracts are available for each county from which the bonds have been received. There is also a statewide index, arranged by both grooms and brides, available on microfiche.
      Adams - Workman
    - Record of Marriage Certificates, 1854-1868; CR.001.602; 1996.06.08; 201.65.1; CR.001.602.1; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions.; Clerk of Superior Court (Item Record of Marriage Certificates)
      Includes record of marriage certificates (generally 1851-1867) and marriage registers (1867-).
  - Divorce Records, CR.001.604; 201.67; Alamance County (N.C.); Clerk of Superior Court; Clerk of Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions; Register of Deeds
    Contains divorce actions pulled from Civil (and sometimes Criminal) Actions and/or record books of divorced women, which notes maiden name of divorcee and the date of notice of intention to resume maiden name. See also series 3, Court Records, for divorce case files, if available.
    Includes divorce actions pulled from civil actions and arranged alphabetically, and a volume entitled "Maiden Names of Divorced Women", beginning in 1937.
    - Divorce Records, 1889-1917; CR.001.604; 1977.08.08; 201.67.1; CR.001.604.1; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court
    - Record of Maiden Name of Divorced Women, 1938-1969; CR.001.604; 201.67.2; 2014.4.64; CR.001.604.2; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court
  - Disinterment/Reinterment Permits, 1978; CR.001.607; 1990.9.4; 201.70.1; CR.001.607.1; Alamance County (N.C.). Health Department.; County Health Department
    County Health Department
    Contains county copies of permits to disinter bodies and rebury them.
  - Adoption Records, 1954-1968; CR.001.901; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; County Health Department
    Adoption files are closed per NCGS 48-09-102. Records will be open 100 years from date of record per NCGS 132-11.
    - Special Proceedings, Closed Adoptions, 1954-1968; CR.001.922; 201.109.4; 2014.4.66; CR.001.922.16 - CR.001.922.20; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court (Item Special Proceedings, Closed Adoptions)
      Adoption files are closed per NCGS 48-09-02. Records will be open 100 years from date of record per NCGS 132-11.
      v5 1954-1958; v6 1957-1960; v7 1961-1962; v8 1962-1966; v9 1964-1968
  - Alien Registration, 1931-1940; CR.001.902; 1974.11.04; 201.77.1; CR.001.902.1; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court
    Contains records pertaining to the naturalization of foreign-born citizens, in which the clerk of Superior Court acted as federal agent. May include Declaration of Intent to Become a Citizen, Petitions for Naturalization, and/or Alien Registration, which notes name, age, nationality, address, previous address, and the names and addresses of five persons who knew each foreign-born citizen registering.
- Wills, CR.001.8; Alamance County (N.C.); Clerk of Superior Court; Clerk of Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions; Register of Deeds
  This series may include Record of Wills volumes; original Wills; and indexes to wills, usually cross-referenced to devisee and devisor.
  See series 4, Estate Records, for Administrators, Executors, and Guardians Records and series 5, Estate Records, for Records of Receivers and Trustees, if available.
  Many of the older Record of Wills volumes may also record estates matters (inventories, accounts of sale, and final settlements) and deeds.
  "Wills, Cross Index to," is usually an alphabetical index by testator and testate of "Record of Wills." Since court reform (1966-1970), this has been known as "Index to Devisee."
  "Devisee, Index to," is an alphabetical list of devisees by last name. It provides the estate name, file number, and docket number. Prior to court reform, this was known as the "Cross Index to Wills."
  - Record of Wills, 1849-1968; CR.001.801; 201.74.2; 2012.5.169; CR.001.801.62 - CR.001.801.83; Alamance County (N.C.)
    Record of Wills 1849-1968. Volumes 1-22.
  - Wills, 1822-1968; CR.001.801; 1976.06.09; 201.74.1; CR.001.801.1 - CR.001.801.61; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court
    Adams - Zimmerman
- Election Records, CR.001.9; Alamance County (N.C.); Clerk of Superior Court; Clerk of Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions; Register of Deeds
  This series may include Election Returns, in volumes and boxes; Permanent Registration of Voters (grandfather clause registrations, 1902-1908) volumes; and Poll Books deposited with the clerk of Superior Court. It may also include minutes of the county Board of Elections.
  Boxes may include civil and criminal actions concerning elections (see series 3, Court Records, for civil and criminal case files, if available).
  - Election Returns, 1934-1976, 1978-1997; CR.001.912-P; 201.87.3; 2017.6.150; CR.001.912; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court
    Unprocessed, roughly chronological order
    Unprocessed election returns (1934-1976, 1978-1997) are in roughly chronological order and housed in 8 record center boxes.
  - Record of Elections, 1897-1968; CR.001.912-V; 1974.11.04; 201.87.1; CR.001.912.1 - CR.001.912.6; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court
    1897 - 1926 1906 - 1918 1916 - 1920 1924 - 1936 1938 - 1956 1956 - 1968
  - Voters Permanent Registration, 1902-1908; CR.001.912; 201.87.2; 2014.4.70; CR.001.912.7; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court
- Miscellaneous Records, CR.001.10; Alamance County (N.C.); Clerk of Superior Court; Clerk of Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions; Register of Deeds
  This series may include Armed Forces Discharges; Cemetery Records; Coroner's Inquests and Reports; Military Records; Pension Records; Personal Accounts; Road Records and Reports; School Records; and truly miscellaneous records collected from various county agencies and offices. Miscellaneous Records boxes may also include records from all other county series that were of insufficient quantity to make a full box.
  - Coroners' Records, 1917-1958; CR.001.913; 201.116.1; 2017.6.168; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court
    Unprocessed, roughly chronological
    Coroners' Inquests and Reports may also include "Record of Coroners" volumes.
    Unprocessed coroner's records (1917-1958) are in roughly chronological order and housed in .5 archival document boxes.
  - Record of Pensions (Widows' and Soldiers' Pensions), 1921-1945; CR.001.923; 1989.05.24; 201.98.1; CR.001.923.1 - CR.001.923.2; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court
    Pension Records may include volumes and papers concerning the issuance of pensions for Confederate service. The clerk of Superior Court served as chairman of the county pension board and maintained the records of application and examination of prospective pensioners, and of payment and receipt of pensions.
    1921-1937 1938-1945
  - Railroad Records, 1898-1919; CR.001.925; 1977.08.08; 201.100.1; CR.001.925.1 - CR.001.925.2; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court
    Road Records may include volumes or boxes of records concerning appointment of road overseers, reports on condition of roads, and petitions for new roads. Boxes may also include criminal actions concerning negligence of overseers and claims against the county for services on the roads. Records concerning bridges and railroads are also included in this series, usually as separate subseries. Volumes may also include minutes of the county highway or good roads commission.
  - Miscellaneous Records, 1822-1939; CR.001.928; 1977.08.08; 201.103.1; CR.001.928.1; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court
    Miscellaneous Records boxes may include records from all other county series that were of insufficient quantity to make a full box. May also include boxes of records for which no series number was assigned, including records of slaves and free persons of color; bills of sale; promissory notes; canal and drainage records; shipping and fishing records; mill records; mining records; timber records; powers of attorney; grand jury records; and witness tickets. Many box and volume titles may be peculiar to one or two counties.
    Arranged alphabetically by type. Includes bankruptcy - Bickle, McClure and Co., 1913, and George Herbert Jones, 1939; bills, notes and receipts - Mrs. S. A. Sharpe, 1898 - 1900; Child Custody, 1898, 1907; Commissioner's Accounts, 1900; Coroner's Reports, 1906 - 1919; Deputy Clerk of the Superior Court, Appointees, 1899, 1902; Financial Statements - Burlington Credit Union, 1836, Swepsonville Baptist Church, 1925 - 1939; Governors' Commissions to Judges, 1907 - 1913; Grand Jury Reports, 1909 - 1917; Gurney P. Hood Commissioner's Report of Banks, 1931; Homestead and Personal Property Exemption, 1899; Land Plat - Joseph Trollinger, 1877; Land Sales, 1904; Lunacy, 1900, 1901; Midway Motor Car Co. Account, 1920; Mortgage information - John Howard, 1922; Pension for Dr. Gaston D. Cobb, 1884; Pension Records, 1926 - 1937; Petitions of Rights and Citizenship, 1899 - 1903; Powers of Attorney, 1879 - 1910; Promissory notes, 1886 - 1902; Registration Records under Constitutional Amendment, 1900; Revocation of License to practice medicine, 1901; and School Fund Records, 1874 - 1876.
  - Record of Notaries, 1898-1925; CR.001.928; 201.103.2; 2014.4.74; CR.001.928.2 - CR.001.928.3; Alamance County (N.C.)
    Record of Notaries Public, volume 1, 1898-1921; Record of Notaries Public, volume 2, 1922-1925
- CRX Records, CR.001.11; Alamance County (N.C.)
  - Miscellaneous Records (CRX), 1861-1903; CRX.001.928; Alamance County (N.C.) (Folder Estate and Other Records, Box CRX Box 8)
    Provenance
    CRX records were alienated from the government chain of custody and have been returned by private donors. They cannot be certified by the Archive.
    Includes one folder of miscellaneous records that left county custody and were donated by someone other the records creator. These records cannot be certified by the archives.
    Estate for George Kernodle, 1903; bastardy records for B. C., single woman, 1861; charge against Sampson Summers, 1864; road petition, no date. (Documents are all xerox copies.) Rec'd for copying on August 9, 1979 from Mr. Frank Kernodle, Mebane Oaks Road, Burlington, NC 27215.